ARIANNA COLOMBANI

I am a sign language interpreter and a psycholinguist specialized in sign languages and deafness. I am currently a PhD candidate in Psycholinguistics. My research interest focuses on investigating gesture learning in childhood and infancy using brain and behavioral measures.

LANGUAGE SKILLS

My native language is Italian. I am fluent in English, Spanish, and Italian Sign Language (LIS). I am a good user of Portuguese and familiar with French, Catalan, and Swedish.

12/05/2022 IELTS Certificate, overall score 8

NETWORKS

26/10/2018 - current

I am a Member of ANIOS "National Association of Interpreters of Italian Sign Language".

Membership No. 107

VOLUNTEERING

ANELLI MANCANTI – Florence (Italy) 01/2018 – 08/2020

I worked as a volunteer teacher of Italian for foreigners.

RECENT PUBLICATIONS

Saksida A, Rebesco R, Colombani A, Pintonello S, Tonon E, Santoro AM and Orzan E (2024) The timeline of non-vocal and vocal communicative skills in infants with hearing loss. Front. Pediatr. 11:1209754. doi: 10.3389/fped.2023.1209754

Colombani, A., Saksida, A., Pavani, F., & Orzan, E. (2022). Symbolic and deictic gestures as a tool to promote parent-child communication in the context of hearing loss: a systematic review. International Journal of Padiatric

Otorhinolaryngology,165.https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijporl.2022.111421

Colombani A., Saksida A, et al. (2022) Assessment of Communication Abilities in Four Children with Early Bilateral Cls in Clinical and Home Environments with LENA System: A Case Report. Children 9(5):659. DOI: 10.3390/children9050659.

EDUCATION

JOINT PhD PROGRAM "INTERNATIONAL DOCTORATE FOR EXPERIMENTAL APPROACHES TO LANGUAGE AND BRAIN" (IDEALAB) IN PSYCHOLINGUISTICS – Macquarie University (Sydney, Australia) and University of Potsdam (Germany)

02/2023 - ongoing

- o Evoked potentials (ERPs) from electroencephalography
- o Symbolic gestures in infants' communication
- o Early communication skills in infancy

SCHOOL FOR SIGN LANGUAGE INTERPRETERS – National Association of the Deaf (Rome, Italy) 10/2014 – 01/2016

- o Simultaneous and consecutive interpretation techniques
- o Conference and liaison interpreting
- o Professional ethics of the interpreter

MASTER'S DEGREE IN LINGUISTICS - University of Florence (Italy)

10/2010 - 07/2014

- o Psycholinguistics
- o Semantics, typological linguistics, Indo-European studies
- o Sociolinguistics, historical linguistics

BACHELOR'S DEGREE IN FOREIGN LANGUAGES & LITERATURE – University of Milan (Italy) 10/2006 – 07/2010

- o Spanish and Scandinavian languages (specialization language: Swedish)
- o Spanish and Scandinavian linguistics and literature

WORKING EXPERIENCE

MACQUARIE UNIVERSITY - Sydney (Australia)

09/2023 - 12/2023: SESSIONAL TEACHING ACADEMIC

o Tutorials of the course Introduction to Psychology

INSTITUTE FOR MATERNAL AND CHILD HEALTH IRCCS BURLO GAROFOLO – Trieste (Italy) 08/2022 – 01/2023

- I worked on the project RC 42/2022 Introducing a novel approach to early interventions and diagnostic measures in children with hearing loss.
- I worked on the project RC 17/2017 Clinical application of new tools in pediatric audiology to improve the prevention, evaluation, and rehabilitation of auditory-linguistic disorders.

FREELANCE SIGN LANGUAGE INTERPRETER - Italy

- 01/2016 01/2023 Interpreter and Tutor for Deaf Students at The University of Florence and The University of Pisa
- 10/2014 07/2022 Teacher Assistant for Deaf Children in elementary and middle school
- $\circ \quad 08/2019 03/2020 Interpreter \ and \ Tour \ Leader \ for \ Travel \ Agency \ "La \ Tartaruga"$
- 05/2017 03/2020 Interpreter and Tour Leader for Travel Agency "Mamberto Viaggi"

BABY SIGNS® ITALY- Padova (Italy)

12/2017 - 01/2023

- I conducted training workshops for parents and professionals working with children (speech therapists, pediatricians, and educators).
- o I conducted training courses on Baby Signs® certification for kindergartens.

LVW LIVE VIRTUAL WORLD Start-up - Florence (Italy)

05/2020 - current: CO-FOUNDER & EDUCATION DEPARTMENT MANAGER

I am the co-founder of Live Virtual World, a start-up specialising in live and interactive streaming experiences in the field of education, tourism and artistic craftsmanship. I am in charge of the Educational Department, where I created educational projects for schools using the live-streaming technology to promote innovative didactic methods and new learning experiences.